WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
- You mustn't make him wait forever.
- I love him.
I'd accept him in a trice
if it weren't for Marigold.
- You say he'll let you keep her.
- That's not the problem. - What is?
If I stay silent, there's a lie
at the heart of my marriage.
But if I tell him the
truth, will I ruin it?
Edith, you're a grown woman
and I can't force you.
But you cannot be married to a man and
leave him out of a secret like this.
- It's not possible and you won't be happy.
- How happy am I now?
Mrs Patmore, you are the owner of
No.3 Orchard Lane, Haughton-le-Skerne.
I am. I'm running it as a
bed-and-breakfast place.
Among your guests, was a certain
Doctor Fletcher and his wife?
They were my first. Very courteous
and respectable, I must say.
Not as respectable as you think.
- Dr Fletcher was a Mr Ian McKidd
and his 'wife' a Mrs Dorrit. - What?
Mr Dorrit is now suing Mr McKidd
for damages related to adultery.
- You may be called upon to testify.
- Oh, my God.
There is some concern
Haughton-le-Skerne will be in the news,
as a site of a house of ill repute.
A house of ill repute?
I'm afraid the rumour
mill has already begun...
but there's a chance that
Dorrit may settle out of court.
- I'll keep you informed.
- Thank you, Sergeant.
Hello. What brings you here?
Oh, Mrs Patmore's the one to ask.
A house of ill repute?
Mama is swanning around the South of
France without a word to any of us.
- I wish Cora --
- I won't hear a word against Cora.
- Mama is being impossible. - I was going to
say, "I wish Cora wouldn't take it to heart."
Mama has exhausted my patience this time.
- But she did give you Tia.
- True. I forgive her everything.
Do you think he will marry Edith?
If he learns about Marigold?
I just don't want her to be hurt.
- Is that it, then?
- Yes, let's go.
- Isn't Bertie's employer
always in Tangiers? - Hmm.
Can you buy one?
Thank you.
The 6th Marquess of Hexham, 39,
has died on holiday in Tangiers
where he was a frequent visitor.
The cause is given as Malaria.
Lord Hexham was unmarried.
- Does this mean Bertie's out of a job?
- That depends on the heir.
Poor Edith. It was bad enough he was
an agent. Now he may not be that.
Don't sound so gleeful about it.
- You should have seen her face.
- It wasn't very funny for Mrs Patmore.
- No. And I'm not laughing, but --
- But, you're laughing.
- How many classes will you be taking
every week? - Five to start with.
Only afternoons between
half-two and half-four.
- What does Mr Carson say?
- I haven't asked him yet.
Don't ask him, tell him.
But suppose it doesn't work
out? Suppose I'm no good?
Of course I didn't know
they'd invited you.
- I would have mentioned it.
- Nobody has been as rude to me as your son.
Why in God's name would
he want me at his wedding?
- Well, isn't it a good sign?
- I'm not sure what it's a sign of.
- Amelia's influence.
- Ah. Yes. I think I agree.
- She is a very kind and gentle soul.
- Is she? Is she, indeed?
- Don't you think so?
- To be honest, I don't know her.
It was all I could do not to
burst out laughing. Poor thing.
Is it funny? Suppose someone makes
a connection between Mrs Patmore
- and her place at Downton Abbey?
- I'm sure they won't.
We should PRAY they don't. I don't
want this story repeated upstairs.
I'm not going to tell them.
Oh, that's the first proper
laugh I've had for ages.
- I couldn't resist telling you.
- Poor Mrs Patmore.
Oh, I know. It's awful for her.
I'm going to have to think of
something serious when I go down.
I had some rather sad news when we
were in Thirsk. Lord Hexham's died.
- Who's that, M'Lady?
- The owner of Brancaster Castle,
where we all stayed last
year. For the grouse.
Not me, M'Lady. I was...
otherwise detained.
Oh, of course you were. I am sorry.
Only it might affect Lady
Edith's friend, Mr Pelham.
He's the agent there. Or was.
He might be out of a job.
How worrying for them.
My romance might not be the only
one to come to an untimely end.
- Have you heard from Mr Talbot?
- No. But that's a good thing.
- It means he's accepted my decision.
- Which is what you want?
Which is exactly what I want.
Oh, I just can't get the
phrase out of my head.
- It just goes round and round.
- A house of ill repute.
Yes, I know what it is, thank you!
Yes, I see.
- Ah, Mr Dawes has got some news for you.
- Do I want to know?
Read it for yourself.
You passed every paper with high marks.
Oh, Daisy. That's wonderful news.
Poor Mr Pelham. First that
terrible day at the racetrack,
- and then to hear his cousin's died.
- It does seem very hard.
- Did you get hold of him?
- Yes.
He's coming tomorrow, on the first
leg of his trip to Tangiers.
- I've asked him here.
- Good.
- How is he? - Sad. He loved his
cousin, and it was all so quick.
The trouble is they've already buried
him and Bertie's not sure what to do.
It's ordinary in hot countries.
It won't mean any disrespect.
No, but, should they leave him there?
Surely the decision is down to
the new Marquess not to Bertie.
Well, that's the thing. He
is the new Marquess... Bertie.
- Bertie Pelham is now the
Marquess of Hexham? - Yes.
Nonsense. He's having you on. He'd
have told you if he was the heir.
He did tell me. But his
cousin was in his 30s
and they all knew the
girl he was going to marry.
But that's absurd! If Bertie's
a marquess, then Edith --
Edith would outrank us
all. Yes. That's right.
- Was he a close relation?
- Second cousin, once removed.
Nobody thought it was possible he
would inherit. Least of all Bertie.
- He seemed like a nice young man to me.
- And getting nicer by the minute.
- With a love of Brancaster.
- Golly gum drops! What a turn-up.
That's dinner.
If we're not too distracted to eat.
- We'll all bow and curtsy to Edith.
You'll enjoy that, Mary. - Hardly(!)
And if Bertie IS Lord Hexham
which I still don't believe,
- he won't want to marry her now.
- Careful.
People will think you're jealous,
dear. We don't want that.
- It's only a try-out, Mr Carson.
- Every day you'd leave at two?
And I'd be back by five. So I
could serve dinner and luncheon.
- No lingering over the pudding.
- Mr Barrow is still here --
- Oh, don't we know it.
- But if lunch does go on a bit,
there's still Andrew and Mr
Barrow and you to see to it.
And what makes you think
you'll be any good?
I don't know exactly. Perhaps
because I want it so much.
There are plenty of little boys
who want to be famous cricketers.
It's not enough to make them champions.
- I just want to try, Mr Carson.
- And so you shall.
How terrible. Poor Mrs Patmore.
- What an unlikely bawdy house madam.
- Mrs Patmore's secret career.
- We mustn't joke when Bertie's here.
- We'll have long faces, don't worry.
- I had a call from Henry earlier.
- Henry? Why didn't you say?
- I'm saying now.
- How is he?
Mourning Charlie Rogers. Missing you.
You're not to ask him to come here.
- Suppose he just turns up?
- Don't encourage him, Tom. I mean it.
- We'd be wretched long term.
- And you're not wretched now?
- Mary thinks he'll throw me over.
- I don't see why.
It's surely very encouraging he's
coming here on his way to London.
Unless it's to break with me so he
can start afresh. He's not bound.
I haven't accepted him.
- Have you told him about Marigold?
- Not yet.
Make a clean breast of it. Please.
- You'll regret it if you don't.
- With my luck, I'll regret it either way.
What are you doing?
Oh. Er...
Making time charts and setting
some tests for comprehension.
- Tests? For the village children?
- You're not expecting too much?
- Who wants cocoa? - I think if
you expect a lot, you get a lot.
- No, thank you, Mrs Patmore.
- Good night. - Good night.
- How are you feeling?
- I'm still shaken. I can't deny it.
- Is your poor niece managing?
- I'm going over to see her tomorrow.
I'll come with you.
A genuine, copper-bottomed marquess
for Edith. Who'd have thought it?
She hasn't accepted him
so he's not obligated.
He wouldn't be coming here
if he'd changed his mind.
If anyone had told me Mary
would hitch up with a mechanic
and Edith would marry one of
the grandest men in England,
I'd have knocked them down.
- Mary has got rid of her mechanic and
Edith is not married yet. - I know.
But for poor old Edith who couldn't
make her dolls do what she wanted,
- it is rather wonderful.
- There's still Marigold.
She hasn't told him yet and she must if
they're to have any chance of happiness.
I beg you, my darling,
please don't let things be spoiled
for her this time. That's all I ask.
All?
I think the wood is right the way
it is. We don't need it any larger.
Mary, let me get him up here.
- There's no point. Nothing's changed.
- You've changed.
It's not as easy as that. I find him
very attractive. I like him a lot.
'I find him very attractive. I like
him a lot.' What a load of baloney!
If I'm in love with him, then what's
that? A powerful urge that fades.
Did it fade for you and Matthew?
- We weren't married long enough but
I'm sure it would have done. - I'm not.
Tom, look I don't mean to pull
rank but with people like us,
we need to marry sensibly.
Especially if we're going
to inherit the family show.
It's a way of life that isn't for everyone
and a bad marriage can poison it.
- He's not an orangutan. He knows how it works.
- He wants different things.
What about you and Matthew?
You came from different poles.
- Yes, but we were young and free.
It's difficult the second time. - Why?
Because you know what's at stake.
It's easier to get it wrong.
- I only see a real opportunity for
you to get it right. - Honestly?
- I'm always honest. - Are you? - Why
would you say that for heaven's sake?
One word: Marigold.
It wasn't my secret to tell.
So, it is true. Well, I knew it was.
Never mind Marigold. She won't
make you happy. Henry Talbot will.
Oh, Henry Talbot, Henry Talbot.
You're far more on his
side than you were on mine.
He's the one for you. Trust
me and give him a chance.
No. And if you want to redeem
yourself in my good graces,
you won't give him a chance either.
Where is everybody?
Mary and Tom are agenting and
Edith's gone to meet Bertie's train.
Are we going to talk about it?
Are we going to sit by and let
this young man's family and future
be put at risk from a scandal
we are hiding from him?
I don't think she has to
tell everybody but I agree.
- She must tell him. Then it's his choice.
- Isn't it up to Edith?
You say that because after
Tony Gillingham had gone,
you thought none of your daughters
would make a worthy marriage.
Now there's a chance and you can't
bring yourself to give it up.
- You haven't got children. You
don't understand these things. - No.
I haven't had children, as
you so kindly remind me,
but I hope I do have a sense of decency.
How long are you planning to stay?
Your cold must have cleared by now.
Don't fight. Nothing's going to
get better by you two falling out.
Hello, Mr Pelham. I mean...
I'm going to stay Mr
Pelham until the service.
I wish you'd call me Bertie.
- What sort of service will it be?
- Not a funeral.
I've decided not to disturb him.
I'll fetch his things and settle his debts
and have a service at home to say goodbye.
That sounds like a very good plan.
- I hope you'll allow me to come.
- I want you to come.
- You remember my sister?
- Of course. Lady Rosamund.
This must be a strange and
unsettling time for you.
I'll say. My mother's cock-a-hoop,
but she doesn't appreciate
- that I was devoted to Cousin Peter.
- I'm sure she does.
Not really. Most people
didn't get the point of him.
He was... so delicate.
But he was as kind to me
as any man has ever been.
Then how pleased he'd be to
know that you're his heir.
That's so nice of you.
Goodness. I'm afraid you've made me blub.
Let me take you upstairs to unpack.
Luncheon's not for half an hour.
- And that's the man you want to trick
into marriage? - I'm going for a walk.
I agree. But Robert thinks Edith's
had so little luck in her life.
Oh, I sympathise, of course, but
we both know she's making a mistake.
One thing. Don't forget Mr Pelham
is now the Marquess of Hexham,
when you address him.
I helped him unpack and he
wishes to remain Mr Pelham
until his cousin's funeral, Mr Carson.
He can call himself Mr
Pelham to his heart's content
but he is Lord Hexham
nevertheless, Mr Bates,
and we will refer to him as His
Lordship. Good. Time to get started.
- Good news?
- Not exactly.
Thank you for your enquiry but
we wish to combine the roles
of butler, chauffeur and valet,
and you seem overqualified.
But please accept our
best wishes for the future.
- What future?
- Don't be silly.
Of course. That's right. I'm
silly, aren't I? Silly old me.
- No wait.
- Let him go.
What was it about Tangiers that
your cousin enjoyed so much?
Who knows? He used to talk
of going down to the beach
and watching the young
fishermen bring in the nets.
How the setting sun would
make the scene magical
until everything was suddenly
plunged into darkness.
- Goodness. How lyrical.
- He was lyrical. He was an artist.
In his heart, anyway.
I don't think this family can
boast much in the way of artists.
Although we did have an aunt
who was quite good at macrame.
So, are you here to settle things
with Edith before you leave?
Mary, please.
I hope so. I hope we can get things
settled but I mustn't jump the gun.
You've talked of your mother but
what other family do you have?
That's it. My father's dead,
obviously, there are no siblings.
It's just me and Mother.
You were joking when you
said she was cock-a-hoop
but she must feel a certain pride.
I wasn't joking but judge for
yourselves when you meet her.
You talk as if we should be scared.
She makes Mr Squeers look
like Florence Nightingale.
Ladies? Can I have a picture?
No, you may not.
He's been there all day.
Well, why didn't you telephone
and warn us? You daft ha'porth!
I'm sorry, Auntie Beryl, I
thought you might not come
and I'm going nearly mad here.
- What about the bookings?
- Cancelled. - What?! All of them?
One man wanted compensation.
For the ridicule.
I hope you told him what he could
do with it! I'll give him RIDICULE!
Now, calm down. There's no harm
done so let's go and have some tea.
This is Mr Molesley.
He will be teaching you history
and English literature.
- Make him welcome, please.
- Good afternoon.
Well, I'll leave you to it.
This term we will explore the years
between the Civil War of 1642 and...
1642 and the Glorious Revolution...
of 1688.
Almost half a century of
change and social progress.
I hope you will find
it as exciting as I do.
Things have changed for you now.
- You must know that you're quite
free if you want to be. - I don't.
Look, of course things have changed.
I was in line for a quiet life,
farming, sport, bringing
up a family with my wife.
But now I'm to be one of
the kings of the county --
always on parade, representing
the people who look up to me,
fighting for causes, trying oh
so hard not to be disappointing.
Oh, I think you'll make
a very good job of it.
You couldn't ask for a man with
a sounder moral conscience.
The conscience maybe, but what
about the courage? Help me. Please.
But can I help? Am I worthy?
The 7th Marquess of Hexham weds the
daughter of the 5th Earl of Grantham?
What could be more suitable?
Mother will be thrilled.
You talk of her a lot.
She has been an important
figure in my life. I admit it.
- But I don't agree with her about everything.
- Is she very stern?
She certainly believes rank carries
responsibilities. But so do I.
That's why I need you. To help
me live up to my own expectations.
We ought to go in.
Tea will have started and the
children will be down in a minute.
- The husband has been bought off?
- Well, he's settled out of court.
- And you won't have to be a witness?
- So Mr Willis said.
But I've still lost every one of
my bookings. I'm a laughing stock.
- I did wonder about the whole idea
from the beginning. - You did not!
It's exactly what we're planning to do.
Then clearly we're going to
have to be a lot more careful
- than Mrs Patmore, aren't we?
- That's the front door, Mr Carson.
I'll go.
Punch is terribly fierce.
I don't think he's a good model
for marriage in later life.
Or relations with the law.
- Take that! And that! And that!
- Ouch, you rascal!
- And that's the way to do it!
- Very good!
Er, Mr Talbot.
Hello, Mr Talbot. Mary never
told me you were coming.
- I didn't know he was. - Well, the
thing is, I was driving down from Durham
and I suddenly realised
I'd be passing the gates.
- What were you doing in Durham?
- Oh, I was doing various car things.
We haven't seen you since
that awful day at Brooklands.
- I hope you're coping with it all.
- Well, one doesn't have much choice.
- Did you know about this? - I might
have said if he was coming from Durham,
then he'd be driving quite close.
Don't think I'm amused. I
dislike my hand being forced.
No-one's forcing anything.
- Now you're here, I hope you'll
stay the night at least. - Mary?
- Perhaps Mr Talbot is in a hurry
to get home. - No, no I'm not.
It's settled then. Carson, will
you please tell Mrs Hughes?
And ask someone to unpack for Mr Talbot.
- I'm afraid you've missed tea. - Oh,
don't worry about that. - I won't.
Hello, Bertie, I heard about your
cousin. I'm so terribly sorry.
Thank you. I'm on my way out there now,
but I wanted to get things
settled before I go.
- And are they... settled?
- I think so. They will be.
Then I envy you.
I would say Mr Talbot has just
miscalculated rather badly.
.. the struggle between the
Monarchy and Parliament.
Oh, right. That's it for today.
Oh yes, er some of you may like
to examine these time charts
that I've drawn up, tomorrow we'll
really begin to make a start.
Would you...?
This is so precisely not
the way to win me over!
- Will you just get off your high horse?
- Why are you interfering?
- I love you and want you to be happy. - Well,
you've got a bloody odd way of showing it!
Well, I take it this is
me you're fighting about?
Yes, it is. And you can dig yourself
out. Because I've had enough.
Oh!
- Have you brought a
dinner jacket? - Yes.
Well, you were very well equipped
to do your 'car things' in Durham.
How many years do you think
it's taken to find someone
I want to spend the rest of my life with?
Living in my family house?
Working to preserve my estate
- and being outranked by your own stepson?
- Oh, I'm tougher than I look.
Oh, Henry, please don't make
this harder than it has to be.
Are you mad? If you're
trying to get rid of me,
I'm going to make this as
hard and as horrible as I can!
Well you're being extremely unfair!
I wish I knew what we should do.
(I'm tempted to tell him myself.)
You think he's strong enough
to stand out against his mother?
Can't we just leave Edith to
tell him or not, as she sees fit?
Tell him what?
That Mr Gregson made Edith his heir.
Some men might not feel
comfortable with that.
Why did you invite Henry to
stay, without asking me first?
Darling, it was half-past five and
the man was in North Yorkshire.
What did you want him to do?
Pitch a tent under a tree?
He must have made a plan
for his journey back.
I doubt he ever went to Durham.
He came up here to see you.
- Who says so?
- The look in his eyes.
Not one of you thinks it's a
good idea! A professional driver?
- With nothing to his name?
- Then give him up. - I had.
I did. Until Mama invited
him to make himself at home!
You can't expect us to be rude. The
man's only crime is to love you.
Just send him away! As quick
as you can. For all our sakes.
She's right about one thing. None
of us thinks it's a good idea.
Maybe not. But she's clearly quite
mad about him, whatever she says.
How was it, Mr Molesley? Teaching?
Oh.
It...
- it was, quite a challenge.
- There's always another day.
I know.
They've got their coffee upstairs
so I'll make a last check.
How are you getting to Tangiers?
Is there a boat that sails direct?
- Actually I'm flying. For
the first bit, anyway. - What?
- I know. It does seem rather daring.
- I do not envy you.
I don't know. Now the commercial
airlines are starting to operate,
I dare say we'll all be flying
hither and thither before too long.
I rather doubt that.
I like the way Bertie makes no bones
about it. He's here to see you.
I know.
The same could be said of me but
I'm not doing as well as he is.
I hope you know what you are doing.
She's quite a handful you know.
- Who's a handful? - My beloved sister.
- Well, she is beloved by me, anyway.
- I like Bertie. I do. But when you
see them together... - Meaning?
If Henry were the new Marquess,
there wouldn't be a woman who
wasn't setting her cap at him.
What about you? Would
you set your cap at him?
- Because if that's why you're not,
shame on you. - Oh, stop lecturing me!
Excuse me.
Mary, wait. Wait!
Look, I made a mistake. I'm sorry.
I thought I could present my
arguments effectively in person,
- clearly I was wrong.
- I can't bear to be manoeuvred.
But you see, I think we
love each other very much.
For some reason, you're
fighting it. I'm not.
My birth is respectable,
so it can't be that,
which forces me to believe
that it is my lack of money
and position that present the problem.
- Aren't you better than that?
- What?
Well, it just seems rather small to me.
Not to marry a man for lack of money
- is the same as marrying him because of
it. - Out of my way! - Am I not right?
No. You push in here,
into my home, uninvited,
in order to call me a grubby, little
gold digger? You've got a nerve!
Mary!
She loves him but she can't control him.
That's what frightens her. He's
stronger than she is, really.
Or as strong. And she's not used to it.
She's a bit of a bully, your
Lady Mary. She likes her own way.
She is and she does but there's
another side to her. He sees that.
- So you were wrong about him?
- I think I was.
- Why are you smiling? - Show me a man that
doesn't smile when his wife admits she's wrong.
- Won't you send me to bed happy?
- Sounds like an indecent proposal.
I meant, give me your answer.
Let me go to Tangiers with a sense
my tomorrows are beginning. Please.
I love you, Bertie.
I've been in love before.
I won't pretend that I haven't.
But I really do love you.
Then I'll take that as a yes.
The trouble is, I'm not
as simple as I used to be.
My life is not as simple.
I... just need to be
sure I'm being realistic,
not living in a fool's paradise
and dragging you into it with me.
I'll still take it as a yes.
- You're down early. - No, I'm
not. Where's Henry? - He's gone.
- What? - He had something in London
this evening and wanted to get back.
I have a mass of letters to write.
- I'm sorry Lord Grantham's left.
- Why particularly?
Because we've got some news and I
was waiting for Mary to join us.
It's not the right moment.
Carson, could we have
some more coffee, please?
Why isn't it the right moment?
- Well, Henry's abandoned you.
- No, he hasn't. I wanted him to go.
- That's not what it looked like.
- Well, that's how it is.
There's no need for this.
Edith, if your news is good, then
we are very happy for you both.
Aren't we, Mary?
See? I told you.
The one thing Mary can't bear
is when things are going better
- for me than for her.
- I'm sure that's not true.
You don't know her. I'm getting
married and you've lost your man.
And you just can't stand it.
- Edith, there is no need for --
- You're wrong. I'm very happy for you.
And I admire you, Bertie. Not
everyone would accept Edith's past.
- Mary, don't. - What do you mean?
- Well, you must've told him?
You couldn't accept him
without telling him?
- Tell me what?
- About Marigold. Who she really is.
Marigold is my daughter.
Will you excuse me?
I beg your pardon, Your
Ladyship, but Mr Pelham, that is,
Lord Hexham, has asked for a
taxi and Mr Carson has gone out,
- so I'm not quite sure --
- What? Lord Hexham's leaving?
Obviously, if he wants a
taxi. What's happened?
Where's Lady Edith? Can't she
drive him to the station?
- Don't bother about it, Mrs Hughes.
I'll sort it out. - Very good, M'Lord.
- Mrs Hughes, how is Mrs Patmore?
- She's still very upset, M'Lady.
But there's nothing to be done.
- Is this about her B & B going
down the drain? - Don't be flippant.
Why don't we pay her a visit? Have
tea there and let people see us.
What a good idea! Why
didn't I think of that?
But if it's to be effective, won't
we have to be in the papers?
Well, the local papers. And it
wouldn't be a news story any more
- than being photographed at a flower show.
- Would Mrs Patmore agree?
- I think she'd be bowled over, Your Ladyship.
- Then it's settled.
I hope you don't mind my saying
that you seem very suspicious.
Do I? But you must admit, your
attitude is quite a volte-face.
I want Larry's father to be
content. Is that a volte-face?
But does your fiance want his Papa
to be content in this way? With me?
Well, you know men.
I'm not sure I do, as it
happens. Tell me about them.
I only meant they dig
themselves into a position,
often before considering all the options.
- And you've considered 'the options'?
- I believe so.
Here's another option for you.
I won't rekindle Lord Merton's
dreams unless I'm invited to do so
by Larry Grey, himself. Is that clear?
I speak for him.
Yes, but you see, I don't
want you to speak FOR him.
I want to hear him speak for himself.
Oh, I see. The plan is to mix up His
Lordship or, worse, Her Ladyship,
with a divorce petition and
the scene of an adultery?
But I want to bury that story and I
need a big event to bury it under.
You have no qualms about dragging
the family we serve into the mud?
It's their choice, Mr Carson.
They're all grown people, surely?
Well, I've always known
that women were ruthless,
but I didn't think I'd find
the proof in my own wife!
And there's me thinking how kind
they were to come to the rescue.
And so they are. Just tell
them yes and arrange the day.
- He'll miss his train.
- Let him miss it.
He can catch the next one. What happened?
Mary thought Edith had
told him about Marigold.
- How did Mary find out?
- Mary is not stupid.
No. And she's not always kind,
either. Was it really a mistake?
What difference does it make?
I'm not shocked exactly. It
isn't that. I promise you.
You have to protect the honour
of your family. Of course you do.
It isn't even that.
You should have told me the
whole story from the beginning.
- You haven't been fair to me.
- No. I don't believe I have.
- Then why didn't you?
- I suppose I thought it might ruin everything.
- You mean you didn't trust me?
- I can't have, can I?
Would you have married me in a lie?
I don't think so, but
we'll never know now.
No.
You see, I don't feel I could spend
my life with someone I don't trust.
- Who didn't trust me.
Do you understand? - Yes.
I'm terribly sorry, of course, but
that doesn't mean much, does it?
The truth is, my life was
about to be perfectly wonderful
and now I've thrown it all away.
- I'd better go if I'm to
catch my train. - Yes, hurry.
I doubt we'll meet again
so I want to say good luck,
and everything else that goes with it.
Good luck to you, too.
I mean that.
Well, you got what you wanted!
Bertie has left for the train
and Edith won't be the
next Marchioness of Hexham!
- Well, that's not what I wanted.
- Isn't it?
I still can't believe she'd never
told him. How was I to know that?
- Don't play the innocent with me.
- I didn't mean it.
Don't lie! Not to me! You
can't stop ruining things!
For Edith, for yourself! You'd
pull in the sky if you could!
ANYTHING to make you feel
less frightened and alone!
You saw Henry when he was here --
high-handed, bullying, unapologetic.
Am I expected to lower myself to his level
and be grateful I'm allowed to do so?
Listen to yourself. 'Lower
yourself to his level'.
You're not a princess in
The Prisoner of Zenda!
- You don't want to understand me.
- You ruined Edith's life today!
How many lives are you going to
wreck just to smother your misery?
- I REFUSE to listen!
- You're a coward, Mary.
Like all bullies, you're a coward.
What are you doing up here?
Looking for you to borrow some
scissors but you're going out.
I've left my workbox downstairs
but you're welcome to take them.
Where are you off to?
I said I'd walk with Mr Molesley to
the schoolhouse. For moral support.
- Are you all right, Mr Barrow?
- Of course. Why wouldn't I be?
- Going away?
- Do you care?
Look, I wasn't to know you hadn't
told him. It never occurred to me --
Just shut up! I don't
know what's happened.
Tom has made you feel bad, or Papa,
or maybe it's just the same old
Mary who wants her cake and ha'penny!
- I never meant to --
- Yes, you did!
Who do you think you're
talking to? Mama? Your maid?
I know you!
I know you to be a nasty,
jealous, scheming bitch!
- Now listen, you pathetic --
- You're a bitch!
Not content with ruining your own
life, you're determined to ruin mine!
I have not ruined my life and if
Bertie's put off by that, then --
Don't demean yourself by trying
to justify your venom. Just go.
And you're wrong as you so often
are. Henry's perfect for you.
You're just too stupid
and stuck up to see it!
Still at least he's got away from you.
Which is something to
give thanks for, I suppose!
I beg your pardon, M'Lord but Mrs
Patmore has something to say.
- I wonder if now would be convenient.
- Of course. Bring her in.
- How can we help, Mrs Patmore?
- Well, that's just it, M'Lord.
I know you're planning to help
by coming over to the cottage
for some tea but should
you be mixed up in it?
- It's my mess, why should
you pay for it? - Indeed.
- Carson? Is this what you believe?
- It is, Your Ladyship.
I wouldn't like to see this family
dragged into a tawdry, local brouhaha.
He means me.
- Oh, I think we have to show a little
more backbone than that. - My Lord?
Mrs Patmore has been loyal to this house
and this house must be loyal to her.
She had made a large
investment in her future.
We can't let it fall away to nothing.
- I'll go now, if I may.
- We'll see you on Friday.
- Are you sure, My Lord?
- QUITE sure, thank you, Carson.
You mustn't be nervous.
You don't know what they're like.
I felt like a fraud yesterday.
And all the time I kept
wondering, "What would they say
if they found out that I was
a servant at the big house?"
What would their parents say?
Why not tell them? Then they won't
have to find out, will they?
- Mr Barrow's in a funny mood.
- Why?
He suddenly told me out of the blue
he hoped I'd make more of my life
than he'd ever make of his.
- I should go back. - Is
something wrong? - I hope not.
- You're on the men's side!
- Never mind that.
- Have you seen Mr Barrow?
- Er, he was going in for a bath.
Oh, my God! Come with me!
Hello! Mr Barrow! Are you in there?
Will you open this door?
Get back!
- Oh, my God!
- Fetch Mrs Hughes.
Send Anna for the doctor but tell
no-one else what you've seen.
- I wish I'd gone with them now.
- With who?
- Mr Molesley and Miss Baxter.
- Well, go then.
- I can manage.
- I'll be too late, though, won't I?
You should still go if
you want to. For a walk.
They might have a break
when you get there.
- Where's Mrs Hughes and Anna?
- Mrs Hughes is in her sitting room.
- Are you in a rush?
- Not particularly.
- Why? - I need you to come
with me to the station.
- Then you can drive the car home.
- Where are you going? - Up to London.
I haven't said goodbye to anyone
and I can't bear to look at Mary.
- She's unhappy. I think she regrets
what she did. - Not as much as I do.
And, for your information,
before I left we had the row
we all knew was coming.
I'm not sorry. At least I'm just
sorry we didn't have it years ago.
Bertie may come round.
I don't think so. He might
have come round about Marigold.
In fact, I'm sure he would've done.
But I tried to trick him and
he won't come round about that.
- Would you like me to talk to him?
- No, but I love you for asking.
We should get going.
Anna's gone for Doctor Clarkson.
Now, we should get him into
bed and out of his wet things.
I hope he won't mind if we undress him.
He's past minding if we put him
in a shy and threw coconuts.
Now you take his feet and
we'll take an arm each.
- Should we tell His Lordship?
- Mr Carson's seeing to that.
Right. Here goes.
- I hate to think he was so unhappy.
- At least it's not gone too far.
Why should you?
.. and maybe one of you will run
the country one day. How about that?
That's daft, sir. Only
toffs run the country.
No, you see, you must never
think that education is only
for special people, you know,
for clever people, for toffs.
- Education is for everyone.
- You would say that, sir.
- Yes, I would. But I'm not anyone special.
- You're a teacher.
I'm a teacher now. But
I'm an ordinary bloke.
I've spent my life in
service, fetching and carrying.
- You were a servant?
- I was. I am. And I was glad to get the work.
My mum's in service. She works
for Mr Travis at the vicarage.
Dad's a gardener at Skelton Park.
But I never gave up on
learning, do you see?
I read as much as I could
and I taught myself,
and I hope to be able to teach you.
Maybe give you the shortcut
that I never had...
Right. The Civil War. Let's start
with the Divine Right of Kings.
Did King Charles really believe
that he had a Divine Right to rule?
Or did he just choose to believe
it because it suited him?
- You mean the King was a liar?
- Er. Not quite.
Kings are like anyone else.
Anna says Edith's gone to London
and I suppose we all know why.
- Do we have to do this now?
- Yes, I really think --
Carson, what's happened?
Where are the footmen?
That is something I need to
discuss with you, My Lord.
Thomas has cut his wrists?
- Yes, I'm afraid so, My Lord.
- God in Heaven. Who knows?
Not many and I should
like to keep it that way.
- I shall say that he is ill
with influenza. - Carson...
- please don't bother with serving our tea.
- With your permission, My Lady.
How sad. How very sad.
Do you still think dismissing
Barrow was a useful saving, Papa?
That's rather below the
belt, even for you.
Look, we've kept him out of the hospital.
Dr Clarkson stitched him up here. He
says Miss Baxter found him in time.
I'll go up in a minute.
I saw Doctor Clarkson leaving when
I got back. What was he doing here?
Mr Barrow has been taken poorly.
He will spend a day or two in bed.
Anna and Miss Baxter will look after him.
- How was it, Mr Molesley?
- Oh. I enjoyed myself today.
- The children were generous to me.
- The children were spellbound.
- How do you know?
- Because I crept in and listened.
- You never.
- I did. And you're a natural.
So, are we to lose you to the
groves of academe, Mr Molesley?
Can I teach a little while longer
before I re-order my world, Mr Carson?
I'm glad, though. You're
a kind man, Mr Molesley.
It's about time you were
rewarded for your kindness.
He'll recover, M'Lady. And he
hasn't had to go to hospital.
- Can we keep it quiet? For his sake.
- That's what Mr Carson wants.
What a day. I ruin Lady Edith's
life and Barrow tries to end his.
- How is Lady Edith?
- She's gone to London.
Which is hardly to be wondered at,
when her only sister has wrecked her
chances of a happy, fulfilling life.
- Lord Hexham won't come round?
- Lady Edith thinks not. And I'm sorry.
What about you? Have you thought
any more about Mr Talbot?
Don't you start. You're
as bad as Mr Branson.
- Why? What's he done?
- He asked Mr Talbot to come here
and he keeps going on and on and on.
But Mr Talbot's not right for me.
- He's not. We'd be miserable. - As long
as you're sure that you -- - I am sure!
I apologise.
It's just nobody can believe
that I know my own mind.
Of course, M'Lady.
- Right. Can I do anything more for you?
- No, thank you.
Good night. And Anna...
.. I'm sorry.
- You don't know that's the end.
- Yes, I do.
And please don't think badly of him.
- It was my own fault.
- Well, I liked him. - Me, too.
Your sister hasn't been helpful.
Mary and I are locked into a kind of
lifelong struggle and I don't know,
it's hard for an outsider to
understand. It's hard for me.
Who invented families?
That's what I'd like to know.
- What time is Miss Jones coming today?
- Five. For tea.
Do we know her real name yet?
She only writes as Cassandra Jones
which is the name on her account.
Perhaps it is her real name, after all.
Well, real or not, she has quite a
following. So we'd better be pals.
- How did you get her to come here?
- I'm afraid I forced her.
Look, she wants more money
which is fair enough
given the success of the column, but
I insisted we negotiate in person.
- Why?
- I was curious. Aren't you?
Suppose she sends someone
to impersonate her,
if she's as secretive as all that?
Let's have a sign if we think
it's the real Cassandra.
Say, "Bananas" if you think
she's telling the truth.
All right. Bananas it is.
May we come in?
Hello, Mr Barrow. Here you
are. To make you feel better.
- Thank you very much, Master George.
- We want you to get better, Barrow.
Truly. And no-one more than Master George.
- At least I've got one friend, eh?
- Have you been lonely?
If I have, I've only myself to
blame. I've done and said things.
I don't know why, I can't stop
myself. Now I'm paying the price.
Strange. I could say the same.
- Mr Carson's told them that
you've got -- - 'Flu. I know.
I beg your pardon, M'Lady.
We're going Barrow and I hope
things improve for you. I really do.
I'd say the same if it
weren't impertinent, M'Lady.
- Goodbye, Mr Barrow.
- Goodbye, Master George.
- So. Today's the big day.
- Oh, spare me.
- Do you want to take Daisy with you?
- Oh, if I'm allowed.
I mean my niece is good but
she might be dumbstruck
with those Lords and Ladies
sitting in my front room.
Come to think of it, how will the
village know that they've been?
Lucy's seen to that. We've got the
man from The Echo coming at five.
Oh? Put up a poster, why don't you?
They're doing something nice,
Mr Carson. Don't spoil it.
Yes. Very nice (!) For the public
to read about the cakes and dainties
His Lordship is guzzling as he
sits at the adulterers' table!
I'm sure there've been a few
adulterers sat at the table upstairs.
- That is different.
- Why?
To say nothing of suicidal footman
in the attic! What are we coming to?
I only thank God that the Dowager
isn't here to witness it.
- I can't believe you came.
- You made it sound so urgent.
Even so, I really
appreciate it. Thank you.
- Was everything all right when you got home?
- Well no, not really.
- Spratt has gone away.
- Did you tell him you were coming back?
A good butler should not need to be told.
Now, where are they? My
broken-hearted granddaughters?
It's just Mary. Edith's gone up to
London. I didn't know when I wrote.
All the better.
But how will we get it all there?
They're letting me have a car. Seeing
as I'm giving tea to His Lordship.
You're ready, then? They've
brought the car round.
Andrew, carry that out.
- And very, very good luck.
- And good luck to us all(!)
In the vain hope that we'll
avoid scandalous gossip.
- You're such an old curmudgeon.
- Don't say you're going off me.
No, because you're MY curmudgeon
and that makes all the difference.
Hm.
Granny. When did you arrive?
Yesterday evening. I spent the
night before in Southampton
and an entire day on trains.
So I've come hot foot.
If you're here to reprimand
me about Edith, please don't.
Tom's already torn me into strips.
- Why did you do it?
- I don't know. She was so...
- Anyway, I'm sorry now.
- You should be.
With Edith, I just say things
and then they can't be unsaid.
Tom believes you're unhappy.
That's why you lash out as you do.
Look, if this is about Henry
Talbot, you should be clear
he hasn't much to offer. Bertie
Hexham is a loss but not Henry.
He's well born, but there's
no money or position.
He's not even a countryman. Not
really. He grew up in London.
- He shoots. - Yes, he shoots. Like
every social-climbing banker shoots.
Well, let's leave his credentials
to one side for a moment
- and concentrate on what
is important. - Which is?
Tom says that he is in love with you
and that you are in love with him.
- Do you believe him?
- Do you deny it?
Oh, for you of all people to talk as
if his qualifications don't matter!
Tony Gillingham had all that I could
wish -- birth, money, looks...
- .. but he didn't suit you.
- No.
He wasn't clever enough.
He wasn't strong enough.
Henry Talbot is both.
All right, Granny, it's not his poverty.
But did Tom tell you, I stood
there staring at a car in flames,
- wondering if it were him?
- I think he's told me everything.
Then you'll know I can't be
a crash widow again. I can't!
I'd live in terror, dreading every
race, every practice, every trial.
- I cannot do it!
- Does he know this?
He'd feel he should give it up but
I don't want that. He'd resent me.
Oh, can't you find me some
Duke? There must be one spare.
So I can put Edith in her place.
You are the only woman I know who likes
to think herself cold
and selfish and grand.
Most of us spend our
lives trying to hide it.
- Oh, Granny please don't lecture me
on sentimental virtues. - Don't worry.
Don't worry. I believe in rules and
traditions and playing our part.
But there is something else.
And what is that, pray?
I believe in love.
I mean, brilliant careers, rich
lives, are seldom led without...
.. just an element of love.
Oh, Granny. You do surprise me.
Oh, I am glad. So climbing all
those stairs wasn't wasted.
No, I would only say this.
First, make peace with your sister.
And then make peace with yourself.
Oh, Mary.
- Is Granny coming back for dinner?
- She didn't say so.
She goes without telling us.
And returns without seeing us.
We're in the dog house. How hard is
that to understand? Now, let's go.
- Sure you don't want to come with us?
- Quite sure.
You don't need me. You're
enough of a headline.
And you certainly don't need me.
- My Lord, I wonder if I might
have a word? - What is it?
With your permission, I'd like
to tell Mr Barrow that he can stay
for the time being at any rate. It
would take a weight off his mind.
That's a relief. I was going
to suggest the same thing.
- Were you, My Lord? - Yes. I feel
quite as guilty as you do, Carson.
I tell you what I blame myself for.
I didn't credit him with feelings.
I thought he was a man without
a heart. And I was wrong.
No man is an island, Carson.
Not even Thomas Barrow.
I ought to be very angry with you.
Summoning Granny to tick me off.
I was amazed she came at my call.
She said your letter was very
eloquent. She was quite persuaded.
- So what are you going to do?
- As soon as Granny left I sent Henry
a telegram to get the next train.
- Hopefully he'll be here by tea time.
- What about Edith?
That's a harder task. I'm
ready to say I'm sorry.
But why should she want to forgive me?
- I got held up. Is she here yet?
- Miss Jones has arrived, yes, Lady Edith.
- Why the mysterious face?
- You better go in.
Ah. Edith.
So this, it turns out,
is Miss Cassandra Jones.
- Spratt?
- Good afternoon, Lady Edith.
Bananas!
I don't have to tell you why I'm here.
Either you know everything
or you're not hearing me now.
The truth is... I love him.
I believe we are right together
but I so very much want to feel
that you're happy for me, as I'd
be happy for you, my darling.
Remember, however much I love him...
I will always love you.
- I often come at this time.
- I don't come often enough.
No, no. It's only a habit.
Actually, I came to ask
for his forgiveness,
if that doesn't sound too silly.
I see. I think that means
you want to marry again.
Well, I don't know if you
have his forgiveness...
.. but you don't need to
ask for mine. I'm delighted.
- Anything else I can get you?
- One more mouthful and we'd explode.
Unless there's another
of those delicious scones.
Of course. Lucy, fetch the scones.
- When does the photographer arrive?
- Five o'clock, M'Lady.
I'm afraid some of the village have
caught on and they're waiting too.
- Are you sure you want to do it?
- Oh, ye of little faith.
- That's it. I'll leave you to it.
- You don't have to go, Tom.
Believe me, I've been part of this
courtship for quite long enough.
It's for you to manage from here.
- Well?
- Well what?
Mary, the last time I saw you, you
threw me out for saying I loved you.
Now you've whistled and I'm
here, but I don't know why.
Because you were right. Because
we are in love with each other.
I'm not sure why I fought it but
I've stopped fighting it now.
I know I'm not what you were looking for.
Tom and I once talked about
how marriage should be equal.
It has nothing to do
with position or money,
simply that a couple should be
equal in both strength and passion.
Should I ring for more tea?
Are you always so cool and
collected? I do hope so.
I'm not sure what you mean.
Your words have made my
heart pound at such a rate
I'm surprised you can't hear it.
I'm hot, cold and can't breathe.
- All because of you. - I must say,
you carry it off well. - Thanks.
I need to know that you're certain.
I am. I believe I've met my match. I have.
I'm not 20, trembling at
the touch of your hand,
but I know that if I leave
you now I'll never be as happy
as we could've been together.
I'm not 20 either but I still
tremble at the touch of your hands.
- Me, too. I don't know why I said that.
- Oh, darling. Thank God for you.
- So what do we do now? Elope to Gretna Green?
- Well, I have a confession.
When I came here last I brought a
licence so we could marry at once.
Doesn't the Archbishop of
Canterbury need to agree?
- Not if you can specify the Church.
- Well, you still need a bishop.
- My uncle's a bishop. - Oh? Good old
England. Some things never change.
But the point is, it's still valid
so shall we get married now?
- Now?
- Well, on Saturday.
You don't want to have a huge
society affair again, do you?
- God, no. I've done that.
- Then will you?
Hmm. Well, I suppose I've come this far.
Give it a moment, Mr Molesley.
Better give it a moment.
If you're ready, My Lord. My Lady?
- We must have Mrs Patmore.
- Of course.
- Oh, no, no, no. You don't want me.
- I insist.
A picture to mark our
gratitude for a marvellous tea.
Are we ready? Three, two, one.
And you promise you haven't cheated?
As God is my witness, I haven't set
eyes on her since yesterday lunch.
- I even had breakfast in my room.
- That was Carson.
He wouldn't take any chances
with Mary's happiness.
Strange. I'll be best man
at both of her weddings.
I hadn't thought of it.
You've been a good friend
in this, Tom. Thank you.
Pay me back by looking after her.
Who's that?
What? I don't believe it! Why
didn't you say to expect you?
- Because I wasn't sure until I got
on the train. - How are you feeling?
Fine. Can you not ask me
that for the rest of the day?
- Could you leave us for a moment?
- Of course.
We'll wait for you downstairs.
You know I'm sorry.
I assumed you would be fairly sorry
unless you're actually insane.
I'm not insane but I am sorry, I
don't know why I did it. Not really.
I've told you.
Because you were unhappy so you
wanted me to be unhappy, too.
Now you're happy again, you'll
be nicer... for a while.
If that's what you feel,
then why are you here?
Because, in the end, you're my sister
and one day, only we
will remember Sybil...
.. or Mama or Papa or Matthew
or Michael or Granny or Carson
or any of the others who
have peopled our youth...
.. until, at last, our
shared memories will mean more
than our mutual dislike.
What do you think he'd have made of it?
I went to his grave to tell
him, which isn't like me.
Matthew loved you and
wanted you to be happy.
I'm sure he'd be very, very
pleased. In fact, I know he would.
- You look nice, by the way.
- Thank you.
You'd better go in and find a
seat. I'll wait for her here.
- Amelia said you called on her.
- Yes. I did. We were talking about Larry.
- Really? Was it productive?
- That rather depends on him.
But surely she was --
The ball is in Larry's court,
Lord Merton, only he can play it.
Those whom God hath joined
together let no man put asunder.
For as much as Henry and Mary have
consented together in Holy Wedlock
and have witnessed the same
before God and this company...
.. and thereto have given and
pledged their troth either to other,
and have declared the same by
giving and receiving of a ring,
and by joining of hands...
.. I pronounce that they
be man and wife together.
In the Name of the Father, and
of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost.
- Amen. - Amen. - Amen.
Congratulations, Henry!
Thank you.
That was a treat, but we'll pay for it now
if we don't get home
to serve the breakfast.
Well, Mr Talbot. You have
swept me off my feet.
- I promise you won't be sorry.
- I'd better not be.
There they go, a new
couple in a new world.
It seems all our ships
are coming into port.
- And Edith? - Of all my children,
Edith has given me the most surprises.
Yes, surprises of the most mixed variety.
A surprise is a surprise, Mama,
and I'm sure we haven't
seen the last one yet.